<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of consumption, and the venereal disease the signs or symptoms of the venereal infection; with the various methods of cure. By T. Nedham, surgeon.</title>
            <author>Nedham, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826151</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826151</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30543</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30543)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1799:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of consumption, and the venereal disease the signs or symptoms of the venereal infection; with the various methods of cure. By T. Nedham, surgeon.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 68, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and are to be sold at his house , the Surgeon's sign, in Martlet-Court, in Bow-street, in Convent-Garden; and Eliz. Harris, at the Harrow, in Little-Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tuberculosis --  Transmission --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sexually transmitted diseases --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A TREATISE OF A Conſumption, AND THE VENEREAL DISEASE: THE Signs or Symptoms OF THE <hi>VENEREAL INFECTION;</hi> WITH Various Methods of Cure. By <hi>T. NEDHAM,</hi> Surgeon.</p>
            <q>Experientia eſt Medicina Anima.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold at his Houſe, the <hi>Surgeon's Sign,</hi> in <hi>Martlet-Court,</hi> in <hi>Bow-ſtreet,</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden;</hi> and <hi>Eliz. Harris,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow,</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain.</hi> 1700.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30543:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30543:3"/>
            <head>To the HONOURED, Capt. <hi>THO. WARREN,</hi> One of His Majeſty's Commanders, FOR THE SEA-SERVICE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as well as the Happineſs, for theſe Four Years paſt, all the Time I
<pb facs="tcp:30543:4"/>
was at Sea, to be your Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, in His Majeſty's Ships, the <hi>Monk,</hi> and <hi>Windſor,</hi> as an Acknowledgement of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Favours, I have receiv'd from you, I humbly beg leave to Dedicate this ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> It is a difficult Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for all that know you, to ſay, whether your Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Courage, or Care be greateſt.</p>
            <p>As to your Goodneſs, your Friends, Relations, Officers, Sailors, Priſoners, Menial
<pb facs="tcp:30543:4"/>
Servants, and private Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I have ſeen and known, ſufficiently to taſte thereof.</p>
            <p>As to your Courage among others, that Action at <hi>Cama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rett</hi> Bay, where you Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Monk,</hi> will for ever ſpeak for you; when all your Decks were cover'd with Blood, and the poor ſhatter'd Remains of dead Bodies: Your inimitable <hi>Courage</hi> then, like Lightning, ſtruck ſuch a Spirit and Life through all your Men, as made them ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, even to engage the Stone-Walls,
<pb facs="tcp:30543:5"/>
which ſecured the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy from them: And you like a Second <hi>Alexander,</hi> as one of the Admirals was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſtyle you, for that Day's Action; or rather <hi>Hannibal,</hi> would have broke your Way through Rocks and Piles of Stone, to ſerve your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <p>As to your Care, you have been pleas'd to make your ſelf a perfect Slave to it, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and late; remarking ſtill all Action, during our tedious Voyage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:5"/>
In a Word, His Majeſty can never want a Faithful, Good, Brave, and Careful Commander while you live, to ſerve him. And that all I have here mentioned of you, is perfect Truth, and not Flattery; the frequent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of other Mens Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I defie, Envy it ſelf, to maintain the Contrary.</p>
            <p>Go on, <hi>Good Sir,</hi> and may you be proſperous in all your Undertakings; may you meet with a ſuitable Reward here for all your juſt, uſeful and painful Services, and in
<pb facs="tcp:30543:6"/>
Heaven hereafter, an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and incorruptible Seat of Glory, is the hearty Wiſh of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most Humble, and moſt Obliged Servant, to Command, <hi>T. NEDHAM.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:30543:6"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE enſuing Lines, on a <hi>Conſumption,</hi> are the Subject of what I have drawn from Ten Years Experience and Obſervation.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible, that there muſt be many Errors contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, there being not a Syllable in the whole Peice corrected by any Perſon whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:7"/>
I expect no Quarter from the Generality of the <hi>Phyſicians, Surgeons,</hi> and <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> on the Account of my publickly telling the World, that I had a Medicine, a few Doſes whereof would Cure the <hi>Venereal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper,</hi> when confirmed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fluxing: However, what I ſay, is Truth, and Matter of Fact, as is confirmed by daily Experience.</p>
            <p>The induſtrious Dr. <hi>Colbatch</hi> tells us, in one of his Books, that he deſigns to publiſh a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Tract of Conſumptions; and that he hath cured many with Acids, either manifest or
<pb facs="tcp:30543:7"/>
inveloped; but, I believe, moſtly with the latter: For, I find by Experience, that most hot Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients, either temperate or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream, as Symptoms and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions indicate, are moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual in a <hi>Pthiſis</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas, in the <hi>Flying Poſt,</hi> I have often mentioned a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, about Six Doſes whereof would Cure the <hi>Venereal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper,</hi> when confirmed as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, as with the moſt ſtrict and regular Courſe of Salivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and often where that ſhould fail, drinking a Dyet-drink af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, without Fluxing, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb facs="tcp:30543:8"/>
or Confinement, I reſolved to write ſomething of it here, in order to give a ſhort Account of the Medicine, and in what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſtempers it is moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual.</p>
            <p>It works chiefly upwards, and often downwards by Stool; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by Sweat, at other times again plentifully by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine; in about Two Hours time the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Medicine is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally over, and the Perſon that takes it may go Abroad, if the Weather be any thing favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:8"/>
It cures all manner of Scabs, or inveterate Breakings out of the Body, old <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers, or running Sores in any part of the Body; it takes away most Pains of the Limbs, tho' of many Years conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance; cures the King's Evil, the Scurvy in its highest degree, the Dropſie, and ill Habits of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; for it cleanſes and purifies the whole Maſs of Blood in a most powerful manner, and cures many laſting and languiſhing Diſtempers, not yielding to most other Medicines.</p>
            <p>I would not be underſtood, that I look'd upon <hi>Fluxing</hi> as
<pb facs="tcp:30543:9"/>
an ineffectual Courſe for the Cure of the <hi>Venereal Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> when confirm'd, but daily take the ſame Meaſures my ſelf, with thoſe whoſe Affairs will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to be cloſely confin'd, and are deſirous of it; on the other Hand, I daily Cure People without <hi>Fluxing,</hi> or <hi>Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and ſome few where once or twice Fluxing hath fail'd.</p>
            <p>When very Young, my Genius inclined me to the Study and Practice of <hi>Phyſick</hi> and <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,</hi> and early met with great Advantages from the plentiful
<pb facs="tcp:30543:9"/>
Practiſe of both, under an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Maſter, late <hi>Surge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Hoſpital; and if <hi>Surgeons</hi> may not be allow'd to employ their <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Study</hi> in the <hi>Practiſe</hi> of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> I would then know how <hi>His MAJESTY</hi>'s <hi>Ships,</hi> and our <hi>Merchants</hi> theirs, muſt be taken Care of, on which the <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends.</p>
            <p>To make a truly Accompliſh'd and Thorough-pac'd <hi>Phyſician,</hi> he ought to live Two Years in the Houſe of ſome <hi>Apothecary,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:10"/>
to acquaint himſelf with all Manner of <hi>Drugs</hi> and <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,</hi> Simple and Compound, and the diſpenſative Part of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> before he goes to the <hi>Univerſity;</hi> ſo will his Study there, and Reading on <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>Medicines,</hi> be more uſeful and advantageous to him: For want of ſuch an <hi>Introduction</hi> thither, when they come from thence at firſt amongst us to Practiſe, what odd and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Preſcripts</hi> do they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally form for their <hi>Patients;</hi> ſuch as a <hi>Concordantia Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordantiarum,</hi> that every <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary</hi>'s <hi>Boy,</hi> behind their
<pb facs="tcp:30543:10"/>
Backs, ſhall ſmile, and readily point at.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> is too ſhort, eſpecially for a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> that would be uſeful and ſerviceable to Mankind in his Practiſe, to expend his Time on any Thing elſe, but the Knowledge of the <hi>Fabrick</hi> of <hi>Humane Bodies, Diſeaſes, Medicines,</hi> and <hi>ſtrict Obſervations</hi> thereon: 'Tis not the Extremity of <hi>Learning,</hi> or being a great <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> that makes a Man the better <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</hi> The moſt learned Man bred up in the <hi>Law,</hi> is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the best <hi>Lawyer;</hi> or in
<pb facs="tcp:30543:11"/>
               <hi>Divinity,</hi> the best <hi>Divine;</hi> and he that values himſelf on that alone, in my <hi>Opinion,</hi> is no better than a learned <hi>Blockhead,</hi> and well-read <hi>Fool.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would not be thought to undervalue <hi>Learning,</hi> but with due Reverence and Submiſſion bow my <hi>Head</hi> to every <hi>Maſter</hi> thereof; of all that want it, I admire it most; and that very ſmall Portion I have of <hi>School-Learning</hi> my ſelf, teaches me better Manners than to ſpeak ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverently of it. I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enough lament the Want of a greater Perfection therein, did
<pb facs="tcp:30543:11"/>
I conſolate my ſelf with the Thoughts, that what I mist of in that, I had abundantly made uſe in the <hi>Practiſe</hi> and <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> in my <hi>Profeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt <hi>Learned Man</hi> bred up in the <hi>Study</hi> of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> without a true Notion of <hi>Method</hi> in <hi>Practiſe, Medicines</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes</hi> joined with <hi>Experience,</hi> is but the greater <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of <hi>Miſchief;</hi> for his <hi>Learning</hi> gives him an unqueſtionable <hi>Character,</hi> and whole Droves of <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> ſhall not be able to leſſen it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:12"/>
The <hi>Management</hi> of <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Diſtempers</hi> is the true <hi>Touchſtone</hi> of a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> to be well acquainted with the <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Steel, Opium, Mercury, Vitriol, Jeſuits Powder, Spices,</hi> and other <hi>Eaſtern Drugs,</hi> to be thoroughly Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of what they will do, and what they will not do: All which are like <hi>Violins</hi> in the <hi>Hands</hi> of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Men,</hi> where all are not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually alike <hi>Maſters.</hi> Among the unquainted <hi>Error</hi> will be endleſs, the <hi>Diſtemper, Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Conſtitution, Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:12"/>
               <hi>Preparation, Quantity</hi> and <hi>Time,</hi> being of ſo great <hi>Moment.</hi> The <hi>Ingenuity</hi> of a good <hi>Phyſician</hi> is not ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in his Treatment of Acute <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> many of which have a uſual <hi>Stage</hi> and <hi>Terminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> either in <hi>Health</hi> or <hi>Death,</hi> whether there be any <hi>Phyſick</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter'd or no; but in <hi>Chronick</hi> or <hi>Languiſhing Diſtempers,</hi> of a long Continuance, the <hi>Caſe</hi> is otherwiſe; and whatever <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> (though never ſo <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed)</hi> is not generally <hi>ſucceſsful</hi> therein, where the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> ſhall be curable, may be reputed to be
<pb facs="tcp:30543:13"/>
an <hi>ingenious, well-bred Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> and know almost eve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry <hi>Thing,</hi> but his own <hi>Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30543:13"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF Conſumption, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>IF to ſave a <hi>Roman</hi> Citizen of old was eſteemed ſo meritorious, as to be gratified with Freedom of the Empire, and thoſe glorious Immunities of thoſe famed SOCIETIES, as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Hiſtorians relate at large, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be leſs deſerving for Phyſicians, at all times, to redeem the Captiv'd from the Chains of Diſeaſes, and looſe them from thoſe Bonds, which have been ever inveterate Oppreſſors of Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30543:14"/>
I do not believe any Man ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionally miſchievous in Practice; and am unwilling to think any Man ſo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, as to pick Straws; or with <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian,</hi> to catch Flies, when the Screecks of a Diſtreſſed calls to withhold the ready and prepared Hand, from cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Throat: No, it rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from thoſe various Hypotheſes, and different Theorems Men make to themſelves, in all Ages; and thereby erect too frequently the Structure on a Foundation of Blood, and the Sculls of Men, than any Proficiency in that Science, that has the Body of Man for its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, in order to the Preſervation of the ſame: For, certainly the Doctrines of ſo many Volumes of Ages are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient from anſwering the Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena of Nature, that they are rather Promoters of Quarels, and made the Philoſophers die old in Controverſie; than produce the leaſt Peace or Eaſe to Nature, to tell us of Four Elements and thoſe <hi>Principia quibus nihil eſt Prius;</hi> and at the ſame time to allow a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation, <hi>viz.</hi> one Element to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable into another, is to allow of one
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30543:14"/>
only Element; which if it may be yet changed into ſomething elſe, it is not before; it is not then certainly a <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium,</hi> the Mutability arguing ſome other Original beſides it ſelf. Principles by the known Rules of the Schools, are not to be multiplied; nor can they, ſince they muſt be found abroad, and exiſting otherwhere than in the Brains of fanciful Men: Why, without tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing of our Brains, may we not take one for all? Why not with <hi>Thales Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſius,</hi> may we not as well think Water the Cauſe and Fountain of all Things, becauſe, even like the Soul of the World, it pervades the Univerſe, and pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates the moſt intimate Receſſes of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? If you ſay 'tis too much a Fluid to conſtitute ſuch concreted Bodies as we ſee, and the various Species that are in the World, you may know that the moſt refined Water is not without a Capacity of producing a ſolid Body and Concreſcence; for you cannot diſtil it ſo long, but it ſhall ſhew you Sabulous and Topaceous Grains; which by the Rule of Addition, may make Mountains, or Rocks, or Gems, or any ſolid Body,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30543:15"/>
you can imagine, to be compact, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial in the vulgar Account. What may not be ſaid of Fire next quick to Lightning? What ſtupendious and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Effects does it produce, making a craſs Body, as Gold, and other ſolid Mettals fluid. And then again, a Fluid by its Power on many Objects become compact, and firm, and ſolid to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Touch; to Inſects, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news Life, and reſtores Nature; and a thouſand Advantages it brings to the Being of Things, which are not very eaſily intelligible. Wherefore, <hi>Plato</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows it a Pyranide Form always aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the Gods from whence it came. And <hi>Cicero</hi> will have the Soul Light like Fire, that it may aſcend to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; yet, glorious as it is, and how wonderful ſoever it is in its Operations; yet we know for certain, there is no ſuch ſtated Species in the World: It is a Creature of every Day and Moment, and nothing more than a Confluence of Minute Parts put into a quick and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Motion. The many Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other remaining Elements, are as irreſiſtible as Sence and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30543:15"/>
can make them: And no leſs material are the Scruples about the Four firſt Qualities and Temperaments ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from them; which Qualities have, it ſeems, been ſubſtantial enough for the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> to erect their Quaternion of Humours, and by a ſucceſſive Miſtake impos'd upon the World their own Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, acting by ſuch Notions only as might by Speculative Deductions ariſe there from. Hence it is, that your Specificks have had their Value, being look'd on as the only Adaequate to cope with thoſe various Humours in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which by reaſon of their ſeveral aſſign'd Appartments, have gotten di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Appellations, when, in Truth, it is one and the ſame Thing preſented in a different Figure and Change of Shape, occaſion'd by the Shape of the Receptacle, in which it lies, or elſe the Figure of the Ducts through which it paſſes: Nor is it any wonder, that the Blood in the Large and Capillary Veſſels ſhould preſent it ſelf under the Aſpect of Purple or Red; and yet by Vertue of ſeveral Percolations become Flegm or Choler, or the like; when
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30543:16"/>
thereby the Figure of the Fibres thereof are changed, and conſequently reflect a Colour far different from what it was before. I ſay, we need wonder at this no more, than in the Conſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Colours of Leaves that run the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Stages of Nature; or of Cloaths that have the Advantage of Art to make them what they are. 'Tis not without good Authority atteſted, that a blind Man with a Touch of his Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, could diſtinguiſh the Nicities of Colours, on the Superficies of any Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and was abundantly recompenſed in the Loſs of his Retina, by the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of another Senſory. We are ſure, whatever may be thought of this Man, that in the Ant of Dying ſuch Things are uſed as contract or dilate, without ſpeaking of any other Diviſion, and thereby making more or leſs room, or ſpace between the Threads of the Cloath, muſt thereby cauſe a Smooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Roughneſs, and conſequently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford more or leſs place to Shade and Light, as the Figure of the Thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily requires. And therefore, ſince Nature is one intire undivided Being,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30543:16"/>
though on the account of Place, ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires different Aſpects; the Mangling of her in Speculation muſt be Butcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Practice, and very hazardous to the Being of Man. As for Inſtance, were I to preſcribe according to thoſe Rules a Phlegmagogue, I muſt conſider the Paſſages to the Head are tedious, and the Burthen to be brought from thence heavy and difficult; in order whereunto I order <hi>Coloquintida, Scam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> or ſome other Elaterious Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, which I muſt be ſure is ſtout e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bring thence the Oppreſſor, againſt which the Complaint is made; and what, after all the Catalogue of thoſe Things we call Phlegm-purgers, do we ſee but a violent Contortion of the Membranes, which by reaſon of their Twiſtings and Strainings, pour forth great Quantities of Serum, the better part of Life, the Viſcous Phlegm ſtill remaining behind, and may have this Motto infix'd on it, <hi>Veſtigia nulla retrorſum.</hi> True it is, that in Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aches that proceed from Plethora's, or any violent Impulſe of the Blood through the Carotidae, where the Serum is not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30543:17"/>
much changed, nor grown lentiſcent, 'tis very uſual to receive Benefit and Eaſe only by Depletion of the Veſſels; which amounts to no more than the thruſting away the moſt neceſſary Force out of a beſieged City; becauſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, they make too much Noiſe, and diſturb thoſe who would die ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and unawares: For, as 'tis ſaid before, the Serum being ſo precious a Part of Life leaves being purged forth all other Parts, to which it was a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle immoveable and defenceleſs, and <hi>Funus Tacitum</hi> behind it: And by too ſad Experience, 'tis known many, even after moderate Purgation, have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been left too obnoxious to the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumambient, but altogether uncapable of Cure for thoſe Diſtempers they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd under, 'twere too great a Task for me to oppoſe my ſelf againſt all the Sons of Art; That were for a ſingle Perſon to wage War with the whole World but in the Name of Peace; would I know ſince that a Diarrhaea is in it ſelf a Diſeaſe, and that very often irrefragable and fatal: How it comes to be a Remedy by Art, and where
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30543:17"/>
thoſe Humours are to be found, which we pretend to bring forth of the Body by ſuch Operations; the not conſidering this has ſlain his Thouſands and Ten Thouſands: And 'twere to be wiſh'd, the whole Tribe of Purgers, ſome few for the firſt Paſſages excepted, were by common Conſent, either baniſh'd the World, or deſtin'd only to the Uſe of Brutes, which are leſs dear to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than Mankind is; nor does the Error terminate in the Hydragogues, and thoſe other Boutefeus to the Body, but diffuſes it ſelf in the Alterants, and whole Courſe of Practice. That Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes are to be cured by Contraries, is neither true, nor intelligible, though the conſtant Maxim of almoſt all Ages, nay; though we ſhould be content to take the immediate Cauſe for the Effect, 'tis not reconcilable to Reaſon or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; for we are not only ignorant in the <hi>Ratio formalis</hi> of Diſeaſes, but as much, if not more, in the Energetical Power of Medicines that are Relatives to them: For, as a good Author ſays, <q>We know not the Vertue of the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Herb that grows, nor the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30543:18"/>
of that which is a common Life among us; for Heat, and Cold, and Dryneſs, and Moiſture, which are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees given to Herbs, as well as Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraments of Bodies, are the ultimate Effects.</q> And ſo far remote Qualities from the firſt Cauſe, as that we want <hi>Ariadnes Clew</hi> to lead us through the Meander, and to the Primary Cauſes, from whence thoſe ſaid Qualities do proceed; and for that Reaſon alone, and becauſe of ſuch an Indication as is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible only by Senſe: For any Man to direct the Antidote contrary, and diametrically oppoſite in the firſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that Quality repreſented, is not only the Way to run the Riſque of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reputation, with a <hi>Re infecta,</hi> as to the Cure, but very often the Hazard of the Patient's Well-being and Life.</p>
            <p>And that this may yet more appear, let us argue it in a Caſe or two that are obvious, and illuſtrating this Point to the meaneſt and moſt ordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity. And,</p>
            <p>Firſt, As to Manual Operations, a Phlegmon is a Tumour with Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30543:18"/>
where, by reaſon of the great Plenty of Blood reſtrain'd, we perceive an unuſual Heat, even like Burning; as when a Member is too near a Fire, the firſt Sign here of Indication is Heat, affecting the Senſe; for, we cannot on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee the Inflammation, and angry Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, but at the leaſt Touch perceive an extravagant and moſt intenſe Heat, and, that before we conſider any other Quality of the Tumour: Wherefore, according to the ſaid Poſition in this Caſe, we ought to apply ſuch Things as are directly oppoſite to this Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and thoſe in an abſtracted No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be Coolers, and nothing elſe, and then the Energy of thoſe Coolers muſt appear, either by repelling this Humour into the Veſſels, that it may no more affect our Sences with the Quality, which we call Heat, in the aforeſaid Part. Or,</p>
            <p>Secondly, It muſt appear in digeſting and extracting this included Matter, and ſo leave the Part ulcerous, which requires all the Intentions to heal and unite again, which yet anſwers not the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30543:19"/>
Poſition, becauſe the Digeſtion required for this Purpoſe increaſeth the Heat to ſome Degrees, there remaining no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſſible Means beſides evacuating this Humour by Evaporation, which cannot be done by cold Stupes and Baths, other then what we have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before, we muſt conclude, that reiterating this Tumour, is in anſwer to the firſt Indication. Now if I repel back, or reiterate into the Veſſels this before ſtagnating Humour, I taint the Blood with Corruption, and entail a ſoft Deſtruction at leaſt on the Patient; for, with the Blood it fares as with the Limbs, <hi>Pars vivens mortuae conſortis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiens eſſe ſolet;</hi> there can be no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, no intimate Mixture betwixt them: The wounded Deer ſhall not mix with the Herd, leaſt it hazard the Deſtruction of the whole Body. There are Thouſands now living, that owe their Cachexys to ſuch a male Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Practice; if they remove the preſent Evil, they bring in far worſe Inhabitants than before: And like cruel Stateſmen in a Commonwealth, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a grievous Burthen, and diffuſe it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30543:19"/>
as an equal Torture to all, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was very containable and ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough by any one Member or Perſon. 'Tis no leſs Art in a Phyſician to provide for a future Health, than to deliver from the Jaws of a preſent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending Death; nay, it is more deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to die at once, than ſee Death and feel it every Day, and that for ſore lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring Years together, <hi>Vivens videnſque perit,</hi> ſets the Houſe always in Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and brings that not over-lov'd Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, a Coffin, into their Sight many Years before the Grave: Theſe <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus</hi>'s, however they came to have the Liberty of Killing, have yet no Licence for Torture and Cruelty: 'Tis far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their Commiſſion thus to play the boundleſs Executioners, and Curſt-like <hi>Indians,</hi> that poyſon for Months and Years at their Pleaſure: I ſay, moſt of the Cachexies owe themſelves to this ſort of Practice, which is a Poſſeſſion like that of other Devils, to be cured by our Prayers, that they may enter into Swine only, and be hurried to their <hi>Exit</hi> by choaking.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:30543:20"/>
The next Inſtance, concerning this Poſition of curing Diſeaſes by their Contraries, ſhall be Phyſiological, <hi>viz.</hi> a praeternatural Heat of the Body, I mean ſuch as is perceived by us in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where it is uſually attended by Vomitings, Diarrhaea's, great Drought, Inquietudes, and Soreneſs of Bones, and the like: Notwithſtanding which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Concomitants, which have one and the ſame Cauſe and Parent, though more immediate with the Heat, and very often appear as ſoon and as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt as the Heat it ſelf; yet, becauſe upon the Touch of the Fleſh, we find ſome intenſe Warmneſs, and upon the Touch of the Pulſe, we find the Stroaks nimbler and faſter than before; we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conclude, the Blood enkindled, the Houſe is on fire; and therefore, by all means, this Fire ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh'd, and put out by its contrary, a (Cooler) this Pathognommick of Heat has made ſo great an Impreſs on al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all Men, that this far-fetch'd Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident of Heat is admitted into all their Definitions of Fevers; 'tis a <hi>Calor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſus,</hi> cries one; 'tis <hi>Calor praeternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:30543:20"/>
               <hi>in corde,</hi> cries another; a <hi>Sanguis ebbulliens,</hi> ſays the third, and a <hi>Luctus internus,</hi> ſuch an Effervency as is cauſed between Spirit of Wine and <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> or between Vegetatives and Acids, which cauſes a Hiſſing, a Smoak and a Heat, the Chymiſt defines it to be. Now, for Mercy's ſake, what Satisfaction can this be for an enquiring Man, when he finds a Definition made up of poor Accidents, and ſuch too as are common and inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to many other Cauſes; and not only to Diſeaſes, but to the State of Health and Encraſie: For, certainly a Man that walks ſtoutly at any time, but the ſpace of few Hours, ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably attended with many Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms common to a Feveriſh Body, his Pulſe ſhall be far more rapid, his Fleſh extreamly hot, his Muſcles much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigued, and his Colour for the moſt part increaſed to the Degree of Beauty; and yet this Man is moſt improperly ſaid to be in a Fever: No, not ſo much as a Diary-again-immerſion in a Bath will frequently procure an extraordinary Heat, a rapid Pulſe, mighty Fluſhings, not any ways unlike thoſe Accidents
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30543:21"/>
we find in a Febricitant Man, in his Diſcumbiture; yet were this Perſon to be treated as a Febricitant, <hi>viz.</hi> with Bleeding and Bliſtering, and the like, as is the common Practice in Feveriſh Caſes, his Life would be moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſince his Phyſician muſt attend him always as cloſe as the Shadow does his Body, for the curing thoſe ſuppoſed Devils, which the innocent Non-natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals inevitably bring upon him. Now if this Definition be ſo deficient and unaccountable, what muſt the Practice on this Definition be but pernicious, or elſe uſeleſs, either deſtroying the Body, or emptying the Purſe; and ſo leaving him fuller of the Diſeaſe than before: On this Definition, the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for the Pharmaceutick part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſuch Things as refrigerate, and mitigate, and overcome this Heat which is thus enkindled and praeternatural, and ſo depraving the Actions of Life and Motion. The thorough Nature and Energy of thoſe Things we call Cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, we are ignorant of; and therefore, if after the Uſe of thoſe Things we reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo the Patient ſurvives, 'tis no Fault
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30543:21"/>
of the Doctor's. I ſay, poor Man, 'tis not his Fault if the Patient lives, for he, good Soul, with his Notion of Coolers, does as much as in him lies, to ſtop the Motion of the Blood, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the immediate Origin of Life it ſelf is nought. But Heat procured from Motion, this certainly is ſhooting at the Deer, and killing the Man; for let ſuch an Arrow flie as this ſhould be, he wants for a Cooler, you'd ſee it fledg'd with Death, as ſure as the Sun ſhines at Noon-day: 'Tis a Mercy then he knows not a right Cooler; if he did, he would be miſchievous as a Plague, and fatal as the Biting of a Serpent. I remember a remarkable Obſervation of <hi>Hildanus,</hi> of a robuſt, labouring-like Fellow, who, when a Town was a fire, employ'd himſelf amongſt the reſt, to quench the Rage, which was ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that to the great Hazard of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing by the Flames did theſe Men venture; that were thus employ'd to prevent their being catch'd by the Flames, care was taken to plant Engines to that Advantage, as might ſpout Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on the Labourers, to cool their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30543:22"/>
Cloaths and Fleſh; this Perſon, of whom the Obſervation is made, being in an exceſſive Heat and Sweat, was from the Engines plyed with their Coolers to the Purpoſe; for, no ſooner was this Perſon from his Labour, but went Home to Bed, and next Morning had through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Body a Gangreen and Cadave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Fleſh; and all this from the cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water alone, chaining up the Blood in the Muſcular Fibres, and hindring it from Circulation. This Obſervation is too notorious to omit any Evaſion; and I bring it to ſhew every Man is a Sufferer in ſome like meaſure, that is under the Misfortune of ſuch an Hypotheſis; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, perhaps, there is not always ſuch an Occular Demonſtration for it, nor ſo plain and manifeſt a Prophaſis in every Circumſtance, to prove the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Danger, and dolorous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of ſuch Means and Maxims: For, if we conſider the Quickneſs of the Pulſe in Fevers, together with Pains of of the Head, and Soreneſs in every Part of the Body, and all the Effects beſides of a Febricitant Body, we find Stop-pages enough, and to too many with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30543:22"/>
their Coolers, to make us fear great Danger, and always ſuſpicious of the worſt of Evils, even Death it ſelf. As for the Celerity of the Pulſe, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly muſt be from ſome Straitneſs and Contraction of the Veſſels, <hi>quoad Latera,</hi> by reaſon of ſome Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Body, from the fluid Blood, got into thoſe Veſſels, and by their Bulk forcing the Fluid into a narrower Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel; as Dirt or Sand on the Banks of Rivers reſtrain the Current; or like the Rays of Light in a Burning-glaſs, which by more intimate Unition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come mighty powerful and dextrous; as by the wonderful Effects we may eaſily diſcover this muſt be allowed, unleſs you'll grant ſome greater Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Blood, full 'twice as much, ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Ryſhmus of the Pulſe in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh Bodies, as was before in the ſame Bodies when ſane and uncorrupted, which no Phyſician can allow; for, upon Suppoſition that the Pores of the Body are then ſhut up, for which Cauſe the Miaſmata's and Habitus of the Body are recoiled upon the Blood, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently augment it, and ſwell it as Rain
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30543:23"/>
does Rivers; though no manner of Sence can or muſt perſwade us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all this, yet conſidering the uſually large and ſenſible Evacuations, as Diar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhaea's, Vomitings, Sweats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which in thoſe Caſes happen; thoſe Evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we ſay are equivalent to the Hali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, detained by the Pores of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, being ſhut up; nay, they muſt be far <hi>ſuperant</hi> (Maugre all the Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Staticks) and the impriſon'd Halitus; and that for this Reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no Univerſal Swelling, nor any ſenſible Action of the Bulk of the Body obſerv'd in any Fevers, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acute or Cronick, except Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Peſtilential, which belong not to this Treatiſe, whatever may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by ſome Eagle-ey'd Men to have obſerv'd in thoſe Caſes, or gather'd by Conſequence, by the Soreneſs and Load that then ſeems to be upon the Muſcles: Yet, be they pleaſed to conſider that what is ſpent upon the Fleſh, is loſt in the Channel of Blood, like the Sea, what it gain in one place, it muſt loſe in another, being not able to afford Spring-Tides in all places at one and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30543:23"/>
the ſame Hour; Let their Pretenſions be what they pleaſe, they cannot deny, but many Parts in the Increment grow flaggy and looſe, and in <hi>Articulo Mortis</hi> a ſeeming loſs of Subſtance appears, as the Sharpneſs of the Noſe, the Hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Orbit of the Eye, do moſt wofully demonſtrate: So if this be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, the Blood ſeems rather dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and abundantly leſſened, and is perverted into ſomewhat different from its former Mode and Figure, <hi>viz.</hi> of a Fluid, which requires Extenſion; 'tis become a thick, heavy Lump, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact and ſolid, which takes up and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires leſſer room and ſpace than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The true Aitiology of the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Pulſe is a Work for the greateſt Philoſophers; 'tis enough for me to conſider, that as Death is nought, but the grand and ultimate Bar to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo muſt every Diſeaſe agree in the Genus, with Death it ſelf, and differ only in Point of Time and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, from the grand and ultimate Bar to Motion, even Death it ſelf: And now I hope by this time, we know what their Coolers mean, and what in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30543:24"/>
Notion, we muſt conclude of their Energy, even an Explotion from all Hypotheſes, wherein the Life of Man is concern'd. Let the Philoſophers take the Diſpute to themſelves, and be content innocently to bandy it in the Schools, where there is no Blood ſpilt, nor any thing elſe but Time: For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready innumerable are the Errors and Evils that have been brought upon the World, by allowing the Principles of the Schools, in the Schools of Phyſick: The World, though five thouſand Years old and more, had the pretence of Phyſick almoſt coeval with its ſelf; yet has not ſhewn a true Foundation of it ſcarce more than fifty or ſixty Years. The Builders which are the Chymiſts alone, have not ſquared to the Baſis; but have bewildred us with their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Diviſions, as much as the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripateticks did before. But we ſhall now content our ſelves with the beſt Reaſonings and Obſervation we can make on this preſent Treatiſe of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: Which is,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30543:24"/>
               <hi>Definition.—</hi>A waſting of the whole Body, by ſome ſenſible Evacuation from the Lungs.</p>
            <p>A Feaver, and a great Ptyaliſmus; together with an Inveterate Cough, are the almoſt conſtant <hi>con commitants &amp; propria quarti modi</hi> of this Diſtemper, and ſhall be conſidered in their due Places: Mean while we are to examine the Genus and Difference of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, in Oppoſition to the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion other Men have given of it: 'Tis very rare to be found in any Author, without a heavy Charge and Complaint againſt the Lungs, as if thoſe Parts, by reaſon of ſome Male Conformation, gave Riſe to the preſent Malady: Whereas the Lungs in many Bodies Diſſected on this Occaſion, have been found innocent and free from that Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer pretended to be generated there in Conſumptive Bodies: Sometimes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, we may allow a Laceration of the Veſicles of thoſe Parts, as in caſe of a direful Hemoptiſis, it many times happens, which proceeds from an over Plethora of thoſe Lodgments of the Blood;—but not always attending
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30543:25"/>
the preſent Caſe, is to be exploded from the Difference already given.</p>
            <p>The wonderful Expectoration, and that for ſo long a Time, ſeems to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate an over Diſtention of thoſe Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, cauſed by ſomewhat very Trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and Miſchievous, till it be thrown off by frequent Coughings through the Ductus of the Trachea, whereby the Part is eaſed and relieved for a Time, by a Truce only, and not by Peace; for there is a <hi>continuum Generans</hi> left behind, which as ſoon as it is recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a freſh Supply, renews the Aſſault, and ceaſes not till it be forced out by Trachea Ductus, as before.</p>
            <p>By Expectoration alone, frequently more than the weight of the Body is expended; and this is not hard to be underſtood, when we conſider Expecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and that very large is the Work of every Day for ſix or eight, ſome few Months more, or leſs, without Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or Abatement; yet are we not to underſtand thereby, as if the Lungs were the only Paſſives in this Caſe; for all the Parts ſuffer and waſte alike, the Head and the Feet partake of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30543:25"/>
middle of the Body, and the Diſcraſie of the Blood, is the ſame in all, only by reaſon of ſome proportion of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, it has to the Pores of the Air-Veſſels, it follows the Courſe of its Fibres, and Lodges where it finds the moſt agreeable Reſt, and Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>'Tis a worthy Query, why a putrid Synochus, where the ſmall Veſſels are moſt affected, (the Lungs, where uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the greateſt Veſſels are, remaining free) ſhould kill in ſeven, fourteen, or one and twenty Days, and why in a Pthiſis, the great Veſſels as well as ſmall, being affected, the Patient ſhould ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive ſo many Months, as we uſually find they do? To this we anſwer, That the continual Evacuation, through the Lungs, is the alone Cauſe of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid's Duration, and Life.—For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, by this Expectoration, the Lungs are diſcharged from the Burden, they groaned under before: The Travelling Blood therefore, has now more room, and is leſs obnoxious to Entanglements, and Stoppages, then it would have been, had the Expectoration not been made, whereas in a putrid Synochus,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30543:26"/>
the leſſer Veſſels, being affected, as thoſe of the Head and Limbs, and the Lungs being free, as we obſerv'd before, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has no ſuch Emunctuary in thoſe Parts, through which, ſhe can ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, and eaſily, diſcharge enough for the Preſervation of Life, and Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Motion of the Blood; But yet, if at any time, a Parotis, or other Critical Swelling ariſes, in a putrid Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochus, 'tis great hope, the Bitterneſs of Death is paſt, and all Clouds for that time are blown over, and away.</p>
            <p>As Expectoration only, is the Cauſe of Continuance of Life, in Tabid Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; ſo does it continually require, a new Expence of Blood, for the Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of the Work; even to the laſt Drop, that is capable of Motion. There cannot be ſuppoſed any intimate Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chyle and Blood, becauſe the Blood throws off every thing, ſo ſoon after its being taken into the Body, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a Diarrhaea, or Vomiting, or dreadful Sweatings, at Night, which ways exceed the Tant-a-mount, by ſome Degrees, of what we introſum'd, but a few Hours before; ſo that the Blood
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30543:26"/>
ſpends ſomewhat of its own Stock eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day, and lives upon the waſting Remainder; (ſome very little part of the Aliment excepted) 'till it be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd up in that Gulph of Flegm, that gives a <hi>Quietus,</hi> to its Motion, for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. How far the Blood is corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or perverted, in this Caſe, will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low different Reaſonings, and fine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, by reaſon of the various De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Gluten, that is thrown off through the <hi>Aſpera arteria,</hi> by Expecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: Withal, we muſt allow, though the Courſe of a Phthiſis be uſually ſhort of a Year, by ſome Months; yet, we muſt obſerve on t'other hand, that it will take off ſome Perſons, ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Portion of Time, ſooner than the uſual Courſe, or Stage, of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, is by virtue of the firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petus of Corruption, or Degree of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, it firſt ſeizes them withal.</p>
            <p>And of an extraordinary Degree of Violence, in the Corruption of the Blood, in this Caſe, I have ſeen a moſt demonſtrative Inſtance: A Man of Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years of Age, and upwards, was through too much neglect of himſelf,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30543:27"/>
ſeiz'd with ſo violent a Cold, that immediately, though of an Athletick Body, he became enervate; and withall, labour'd under all the Symptoms of a Tabid Body, to a Degree, beyond all the Obſervations, I ever yet could make of Conſumptive Bodies, even when they were in the Jaws of Death; for, beſides all the reſt of the Maladies he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went, in a high Meaſure, his Expecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was extream, and ſo intolerably faetid, as no inveterate Ulcer could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed it, though near a Gangreen, and utmoſt Peril of Life: I need not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, it was from any Ulcer ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly produc'd in the Lungs, but rather from a bare Perverſion of the Blood, and other Humours of the Body; as we find in Cadaverous Fleſh, when 'tis expos'd to ſome Tempers of Air, eaſily contracts an ungrateful Odour, which our Senſories cannot well undergo.—I ſcarce remember a more ungrateful Smell from a dead Body, and though I certainly know peſtilential and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Diſtempers, (thoſe Thunder-bolts to Nature, that cut Men off preſently) cauſe the Blood to ſuffer in the higheſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30543:27"/>
Degree of Degeneracy; yet, ſcarce is the Author to be found, that relates more of a Faetor in thoſe Caſes, than this Example mentions to us.</p>
            <p>What we were wont to call, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements of the Blood, (amongſt which Flegm is reckoned) is here the Blood it ſelf, in Subſtance and Quantity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Diſcraſie and Diſaſter; which, indeed, is in ſo great a meaſure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and degenerated to ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as far exceeds all your celebrated Receipts, and Practice that is ordinarily ſhown, in this Caſe, to make a Regreſs, to the Habit of the Body, from that almoſt Privation, the ſuffering part, to wit, the Blood undergoes, in this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity.</p>
            <p>I would not be underſtood, as if this Caſe were incurable, but I mean, that this hardened Flegm cannot be commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuted by the higheſt Liſt of Practice, that has now obtain'd amongſt all the Pretenders, to the Cure of this Evil;—Not ſo comminuted, I ſay, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix with the more fluid part of the Blood, but is by them ſent away, as a Pepaſmus, pretending, by the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectoration,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30543:28"/>
to preſerve that part of the Blood, that is yet capable of Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Life, from ſtriking on the ſame Rocks and Shelves, the other parts had done before. Whereas by this Pepaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, they pretend we ſee nothing leſs, than perfect Life, exhauſted and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, the Weight of the Body, many times over-ſpent, and the laſt Drop ready, and neceſſitated to the ſame Corruption, and Expectoration as the firſt.</p>
            <p>Of the Inefficacy of this Method, by way of Expectoration, is ſufficiently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, and we perſwade our ſelves, that notwithſtanding this Faetor, and thoſe other direful Symptoms we ſpeak of, we ſee no Impoſſibility at all, why this unhappy Man was not as capable of a Cure, as one that has a cutaneous Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, or has in any Limb contracted a Faetor, treatible by Manual Operation, and bare Surgeons Art.</p>
            <p>The ſeveral Degrees of Corruptions, in the various Species of Things, is no leſs curious a Speculation, than the Ways of Preſervation of Bodies, if not the ſame; for, without the one, we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30543:28"/>
can but blindly, and fortuitouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the other, nor preſerve the Body, on which we are concern'd, but at the greateſt Uncertainty and Random.—'Tis the Work of many Tomes and Years, to conſider the ſeveral Degrees of Corruption and Perfection, as they all deſerve; and I wiſh, I may live to ſee it done, by the Hands of ſome few Men, who I'm ſure will make Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of moſt of what they write, and ſatisfie the Knowing part of the World, that <hi>Democritus</hi>'s Well is not bottomleſs to the induſtrious and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Enquirer of Nature's Treaſures;—of this we may be abundantly ſatisfied, that the Qualities we are now ſpeaking of, are as comprehenſive, as the Objects of that Senſe can be, which they effect in their <hi>Genera</hi>'s, and far more delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in their Speculation, ſince we are aſſured, that the ultimate Corruption in ſome Species of Things, is as grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and pleaſing, as the moſt odoriferous Drug; while on the contrary, other Things in their Putrefaction are deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to an utter Averſion and Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, as moſt unpleaſing and intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30543:29"/>
to our tender Senſory, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>The Fever that accompanies this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, is called Hectical, <hi>ab</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> having enkindled the whole Maſs of Blood, and other Juices of the Body, even all the Stamina's of Life and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:—But by the Learned's leave, this is obtruding upon the World <hi>verba pro farinis;—</hi>here's Authority inſtead of demonſtrative Reaſon, and Bunches of Multitudes for revealed Truths: For, though I ſhould grant and allow, a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in this Caſe, yet I hope, they'll be pleas'd to let us know, what an Hectick is, and whether by any means, it may not be adapted to any other ſort of Fever, to be called Hectical, more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, and Specifically, than to this: For, in this ſort of a Fever, we call a Conſumption, we find People for the moſt part Cold and Languid, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly wanting the pleaſing Comforts of Heat and Warmth; as we ſhall ſee by and by: Moſt true it is, while the extream parts ſuffer, under a Fit of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency, the middle Region, like Fire in a reverberatory Furnace, can only
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30543:29"/>
reflect upon it ſelf, to grow thereby the more intenſely Hot, not being able by reaſon of its Clauſure, to extend it ſelf any way, either for its own Liberty, or Refreſhment of other parts, that ſtand ſo much in need thereof; and by this Straitneſs, and this Impriſonment of the Blood, in the middle Region, they may apprehend ſome Cauſe for a Hectick, the Inflammation being ſo extream, and ſenſible in that part: Which, yet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, argues no more a Hectick, than a Phlegmon, or an Eryſipelas, in any Member, or Part, could do; for, in both thoſe Caſes, there is almoſt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable Inflammation, there is the Blood chain'd up, with a <hi>non ultra, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trave;</hi> and yet, he that ſhould pretend to be ſuch an Alpheiſt in Phyſick, as to call either of thoſe Hectick, might be rightly concluded, to have an Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in his Brain, great enough to amount to a Phrenſie, and wants the Air, and Hellebore of the <hi>Anticyra</hi>'s to cure him.</p>
            <p>Beſides, I look on Hectick, as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting ſomewhat Habitual, to be Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal like the Soul, all in all, and all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30543:30"/>
in every part, and not Topical, as is this our Inſtance, where the Blood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pent in a ſtrait part, is forc'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud all other places of its benign Streams, and pleaſing Reflections. But however, a Fever we allow it, and as ſuch, it differs from a Synochus, not only in the Duration of time, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, becauſe it has long Intermiſſions of Heat; and then again, it differs from intermitting Fevers, becauſe it is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly free from the Fit of Exhorrency; and beſides, is not obliged to the ſtrict Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxiſms of Heat, and Cold, and Sweat, at certain Hours, as the Intermitting eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially is.</p>
            <p>Whether the Paroxiſms of an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Fever depends on the <hi>Succus Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritius,</hi> is not eaſily prov'd, nor credit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But thus much is certain, in our Caſe;—Our Paroxiſms of Heat, owe their Original, for the moſt part, to Things introſum'd, or other of the Non-naturals and Accidents, from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. 'Tis obſervable, that after eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though a ſmall Pittance, which is as much as their poor Stomachs can diſpence withal, the Blood ſeems trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30543:30"/>
and appears in Scarlet Fluſhings, and greater Quantities in the extream Parts, than at other times it uſually does, no leſs is obſerv'd, in Drinking, or Motion, the leaſt of which, is ſome Violence to Tabid Bodies; the drowſie Blood is awakened, and ſhows a mighty Muſter, and a more ſeeming numerous Force, than in Sane Bodies is commonly to be found: Now this Heat, and thoſe Fluſhings, which continue a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time, are very rarely followed by any ſuch Sweats, as we ſee are the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Concomitants, and eternal Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods of intermittent Feavers, and Agues.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, there are Sweats in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Bodies, more certain and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, than any Paroxiſm again that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to this deplorable Evil; but as we ſaid before, thoſe Sweats are no ways depending, nor by any means con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to thoſe Heats, or Fluſhings we ſpoke of juſt now, but due purely to Sleep and Diſcumbiture; for, in Sleep, the Pulſe moves not only faſter than in vigilant Bodies, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drives more Blood to the Habit of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30543:31"/>
the Body; but the Weight and Warmth of the <hi>Stragulae</hi> preſs the Muſcles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly, all which contributes to that Expreſſion, we call Sweat, and this as conſtant and periodical as Night it ſelf. After which Deluge of Sweat, (for 'tis in extream) the Body grows cold, and languid, and enervate, being ſo great a Sufferer, by the Loſs of ſo much Strength and Spirit; ſo that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Parts, ſeem to be left even Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, till refreſh'd by means of the Non-naturals, or the like, it begins the Dance of Heat and Fury, as we ſaid before.</p>
            <p>Thoſe are the conſtant Scenes, and this the uſual Prophaſis, during the whole Stage of this grievous Malady: As to that part of it, which reſpects the Fever; which, indeed, by reaſon of its Expence, and mighty Profuſion, were enough of it ſelf, to cauſe a Phthiſis, (though here it be only as a Concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, or ſomewhat Symptomatical,) as it frequently happens in long Quartane Agues; but yet, as if this were not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to precipitate the Body to the Grave; beſide this mighty Expence and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30543:31"/>
Profuſion, we have been talking of, there is frequently a <hi>Diarrhaea Colliqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva,</hi> and ſometimes a Lientery; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 'tis obſervable, that this Diarrhaea does not tread on the Heels, nor follow ſo cloſe the Introſumption of Meats, and Drinks, and the like, as the Feveriſh Heat and Fluſhings, we have been juſt ſpeaking of, certainly does, but has the Intermiſſion of ſome Hours, ſometimes four or five; the Time Dr. <hi>Gliſſon</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows after Refection, for natural Stools, before it follows; yet, then the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief is, 'tis more than ordinary fluid, and looſe, as if it were cauſed by Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terium, or ſome poyſonous Purgation, inwardly taken.</p>
            <p>This Diarrhaea diſheartens more Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, than all the other Symptoms, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending this Caſe, and makes them cry out with a <hi>Conclamatum eſt,</hi> all's in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, and irrevocably loſt and gone: Certain it is, the whole oeconomy is diſturb'd thereby, eſpecially, if we go the old Way of Reckoning, three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, then we muſt conclude an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the firſt Concoction cannot be corrected in the other two that follow;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30543:32"/>
and therefore, the Blood is too much burthen'd with an ungrateful Load, it knows not how to diſpoſe of, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge; but ſuffers a Seceſſion of Parts, which is ever pernicious, in the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to the ſuffering Creature, in its well-being of Life and Health;—per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, and ſometimes fatal it is, when it is a Diſeaſe of it ſelf, without the Adjuncts of any other Diſcraſie; But when 'tis the Conſequence of a greater Diſeaſe than it ſelf, as in this Caſe it is, it carries an <hi>Ilias malorum</hi> with it, and portends the greateſt Difficulty, if not Deſpair and Ruine; for it does not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompany thoſe other expenſive E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuations, we mentioned before, but through want of Appetite, the Body is denied the Recruits and Refreſhments, which ſhould ſupply the Place of the aforeſaid Profuſion; And no Wonder is it then, if thoſe Rivers of Blood and Juices are at laſt dryed up, ſince the Sea upon the ſame Occaſion, would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come dry Land.</p>
            <p>In a Word, a Diarrhaea is not only as miſchievous in this Confederacy, but ſomewhat more unnatural than any of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30543:32"/>
the reſt; for here we have Water for Solid, we have Faintneſs inſtead of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, we have a Deluge inſtead of the natural Flowings of Life and Well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: If you compare it with Expecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Sweating, you'll find it more unnatural; for by Expectoration, of what ſoever it be, we find the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement much of the ſame Conſiſtence and Texture; we obſerve that Sweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is no more than Tranſpiration pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated, and the Fugitive Miaſmata's being now collected, become obvious to Sence, as much as the Miaſmata's of Tranſpiration were to reaſon before: But in this of a Diarrhaea, thoſe Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that uſually were ſolid and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, are now thin and fluid as Water. Neither is the Frame of the Lungs ſuch, nor the curious Texture of the Skin any way ſo made, as to comminute a thick Body into a Fluid; but on the contrary, their Frame is ſuch, as to ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate thoſe Recrements they receive from a Fluid, to a Conſiſtence, before they ſend them forth by Excretion.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:30543:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:30543:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:30543:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:30543:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:30543:35"/>
To thoſe Sallies of Life, and almoſt conſtant Sluces of Tabid Bodies, we may add, as a Cataſtrophe, an Haemop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſis, which though it happens uſually not till the laſt Stages of this Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, yet equals them all in a direful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect and Prognoſtick: In the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, we mention'd even now, there are Recrements and elaborated Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, but in this, downright Blood and Life, Strength, Nectar and Spirit alone; as if Nature, giving up all for loſt, came forth unattended, and bluſh'd at the cruel Dealings of its offending and mortal Enemy. 'Tis then common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it appears, when all its Channels are cramm'd with Corruption, and it ſelf forc'd (not without ſtrong Palpitations) to take that Paſſage, <hi>Qua data porta.—</hi>Thoſe are the Profuſions of Life, and thoſe, the uſual Ways, by which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture decays and flies away in Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Bodies, which we ſee are little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior, to what we find in the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and peſtilential Diſtempers; for in the Enumeration of the Evils that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Peſtilence, none ſeem more direful than Haemoptyſis, and Haemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhages,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30543:35"/>
ſtrong Palpitations, and Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copes, which ſometimes in this Caſe, may likewiſe be found, which if Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone, the Subject of Senſe; <hi>viz.</hi> of Pains and Eaſe, were to be conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, might paſs for Mercy, ſince they take away <hi>Ex improviſo,</hi> without the Warnings of Pains and Torture, while Tabid Bodies die by Peice-meals, and ſee themſelves cut down alive, by the Cruelty of thoſe Executioners.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the Diſeaſe it ſelf, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Concomitants, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Adjuncts which we meet with in the Courſe of this Diſaſter: We will next conſider the ſeveral Cauſes, both procatarctick and evident, from which this Malady may have its Origin, or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning:—But firſt, we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that 'tis either Primary, without the Precedence of another Diſtemper, or elſe conſequential to ſome Diſtemper that has produc'd it, and by its Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſo perverted the Blood, as to cauſe this Malady in the Body, we call a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:30543:36"/>
If we conſider it as Primary, without the Precedence of another manifeſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, it proceeds from theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cauſes:</p>
            <p>Firſt, From a natural Diſcraſie of the Blood it ſelf, ſuch as is <hi>ex traduce,</hi> or in the Elements of Generation from the Parents, and is what we call a natural Conſumption:—And this is ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that whole Families have been proſtrated, and that to a certain Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Years, which was a <hi>non ultra,</hi> they could not by reaſon of the Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their Conſtitution paſs over, and leave behind them: And this without any evident Cauſe, as is required, to the Reducing of an Athletick Body, to the like Caſe and Miſery.</p>
            <p>A Perſon of a macilent, but laborious Conſtitution, was ſeiz'd without any evident Sign of Error in the Non-natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals (which uſually are the Cauſes in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſons that labour under this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe) with a horrid Haemoptyſis, as affrighted all the Spectators and Friends that were about him, and continued by Periods for ſome Days in that bloody
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30543:36"/>
Condition, with loſs of Appetite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By the repeated Inſtances of ſome of his Companions, he addreſs'd himſelf to an old Woman, who ſtops the bleeding, which was preſently ſucceeded by a Hoarſeneſs, and ſmall Cough; for which he takes the Country Air, where he was delivered from thoſe troubleſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions; but returning again to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> he brought thoſe troubleſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions again with him, and relapſed to much the ſame Condition as before he went, bleeding excepted, he declined all further Means; for, that he too freſhly remembred the lamented <hi>Exits</hi> of Three or Four of his near Relations, who from Athletick Bodies, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd by an unhappy Conſtitution, even to Shadows of Humane Bodies, before they reach'd the Grave.</p>
            <p>Indeed, this ſort of Conſumption, which is <hi>a traduce,</hi> is accountable to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a ſlender, and a very weak Contexture of the Blood, either poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively as to the Fibres, which being brittle and too terrene, after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſting of ſo many Years, not only diminiſh themſelves, but become inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30543:37"/>
to all other Parts; or reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in regard of the Mixture, are forc'd through length of Time, to forge that Contract, and Aſſociation irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, which before they had with other Parts, and to which they were united.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This Diſtemper is produc'd from an evident adventitious Cauſe, and that uſually by the Air, or Meats, or Drinks, or Paſſions of the Mind: That 'tis produc'd by the Air, is known and acknowledg'd by the moſt vulgar and meaneſt ſort: The <hi>Frigus Suſceptum</hi> is a Stranger in no Country, nor Nation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun.—We live in a State of War not only among our ſelves, but even with the Elements; as if they (if any ſuch be allowable) do with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe very Things that incur our Senſes, <hi>viz.</hi> Earth, Water and Air, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them only for variety of Beings, that make up a Part of the World, thoſe very Things enjoy every one their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Places only by Force and blind Neceſſity, and prey upon one another, as profeſs'd and irreconcilable Enemies; and on all other Things, as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30543:37"/>
taking Advantages of thruſting out, or preſſing too hard all ſuch Bodies as are within their Sphere.</p>
            <p>Of the Elaſtick Power of the Air, ſuch ſtupendious Things are related, as now the poor, unhappy Philoſopher, of whom <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeaks, is more pittied than blam'd, for eſteeming it a God;—for it like a Deity, can kill as well as make alive; witneſs the wonderful Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Pneumonick Engines, and Neighbourhood of great Warlike In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Death; and like a mighty Empire, were it not poiz'd by its own Weight, there is nothing in the World, but it would precipitate to Death and Deſtruction, quick as Lightning, or the Thoughts of the moſt active Soul in the World: And, although the wiſe Architect has confin'd it, and ſaid to it like the Sea; Thus far ſhalt thou go, and no further:—Yet ſuch is the Exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs and Strugling of its very Being and Eſſence (and the Eſſences of Things we know GOD will never deſtroy) that through the minuteſt, and (to all other Things) imperviable Paſſages it extends ſelf, and rejoyces in the Expanſion and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30543:38"/>
Liberty it can procure, though to the Ruine of other Bodies: And ſince it lies in wait, like a ſlumbring Lion, to ſeize that Body, which, by reaſon of the Tenderneſs of its Texture and Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Frame, muſt either ſhrink, or give way to its Springineſs and Force; no wonder, if very oft the Blood of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Bodies, that by reaſon of its Fluidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, cannot be very compact and reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, couch under the Load of a Force much greater than its own.</p>
            <p>We have already ſaid, the Air has its <hi>Aequilibrium,</hi> as a Circumambient of Bodies, and nothing elſe to keep it from deſtroying thoſe Bodies to which it is a place; and therefore, if at any time, either ſide, or part of the Circumam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient be pantherous and violent; as we find 'tis in the Caſe of Gun-powder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we ſee all Bodies ſet in any Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parallel, ſuffer thereby, and ſeem to complain of an unwonted Violence done unto them. And though, when the Cold does ſeize us, as often it will, when after great Agitation and Fatigue, the Body ſhall be expos'd, or by bare Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in an Evening-Air, or by putting
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30543:38"/>
off Cloaths, or by walking in malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Winds; of which <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſpeaks ſo Divinely: I ſay, in thoſe and many other Caſes, though in that inſtant we find no Alteration; yet ſhortly after, in a few Hours or Days, we may digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Cauſe, by complaining of Sore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Thickneſs, and a thorough In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition of the whole Body, and by recalling our Thoughts, point out that unhappy Moment which firſt began the Dance and Torture we at preſent feel:—We find this ſo general, and to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that the moſt Pancratick Bodies are not exempted, but frequently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the lamented Subjects of the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of this Circumambient, which we juſtly have made, and prov'd to be a Cauſe of this deplorable Evil.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Beſides the Air, there is another of the Non-naturals, <hi>viz.</hi> Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Meat and Drink, that's very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently an evident and moſt manifeſt Cauſe of this Conſumption: As 'tis ſaid by the Philoſophers, we are nouriſh'd by Things of like nature with our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence; ſo ſure it is, we periſh and die
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30543:39"/>
daily by what we are nouriſh'd.—There is no Perſon, but after a Refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on finds himſelf not only not ſo light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as before, but withal, very much in heat (except cold Weather be the Hindrance) that ſeems to proceed from ſome Reluctancy and Contention that is within, ſome difficulty the Blood finds in receiving the groſs Fibres of thoſe Foods we uſually eat. 'Tis the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ſome very learned Men, that all the World, before the Floud, abſtain'd from the Fleſh of Animals, dedicating it to a more noble Deity than what dwells in the Belly, and temperating themſelves to a more delicious Variety of what the Earth, either of her ſelf, or by being cultivated, did produce, out-liv'd the now Wonder of half De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cads of a Thouſand Years, even to that time, when the Thred of Life not wounded nor cut, but quite worn by Age and Time, brought them to the Grave in a good old Age, and Peace.—This was the Golden Age, of which the Poets ſpeak of no acute Diſtemper then like a Chain'd Shot, to cut a Man in two, no Chronick to torment him,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30543:39"/>
his Body was the leaſt of his Care, and Eaſe and Peace were inſeparable Jewels of his Life, becauſe he knew not how to deſtroy himſelf, and that Gluttony was a ſtranger to him.</p>
            <p>Not only to the Quantity of Things introſum'd, but to the Quality, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable a great part of thoſe Miſeries, we every-where find Humane Nature oppreſſed withal; there are your <hi>Dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pepta</hi> ſerv'd up to the Table every Day, and Death garniſh'd round in many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes.—There are but few that can digeſt Blood, and not many more that can away with the inherent Crudities, that are inſeparable from the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Being of Multitudes of Things, we daily uſe.</p>
            <p>I know not why Antipathy ſhould be reckon'd an occult Quality, when a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall be ſenſible of the Vicinity of ſome diſagreeable Body, though nothing ſhall appear to Sight, or trouble him: Doubtleſs, from ſome former Injury re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, either by himſelf or Parent, by this very thing which now by its diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Miaſmata's alarms the Blood again, a dangerous and irreconcilable Enemy:—Seldom,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30543:40"/>
indeed, is there any greater hurt done in this Caſe of Antipathy, than raiſing ſome Diſorder and Diſquietude in the Blood, which by this means is ſufficiently forewarn'd of meddling with what it knows is averſe to its Nature and Well-being; the Danger is then only when we either greedily take in ſuch Things as are either crude of themſelves, or by ſome preſent unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Circumſtance of our Bodies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſo to us in that juncture of time only.</p>
            <p>A young beautiful Virgin, the Child of moſt robuſt and hail Parents, feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Night on Pidgeons, ſomewhat too green, fell into a grievous Vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Looſneſs, and ſoon after grew Tabid irretrievably, notwithſtanding the beſt Application of Means could be procur'd for her.</p>
            <p>A Man of a moderate Conſtitution, by eating heartily of Eels (though well prepared) greatly hazarded the Tone of his Blood, and with very great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty was ſav'd from an Atrophy caus'd thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:30543:40"/>
Thoſe are Inſtances to be pittied and deplored, becauſe thoſe were but ſingle Acts, not voluntary Habits of Gluttony and Luxury, and would have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, either by a Pre-experiment, or preſent Counſel of Abſtinence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, while others, rich and luxurious, ſet no Boundaries to their Deſires, but ſatiate with the preſent Dainties, are quick in the Purſuit, and daring in the Entertainment of other Novelties, they are altogether ignorant of.</p>
            <p>'Tis in this Caſe, methinks, a great Advantage to be poor and needy, to eat the Bread with Care, and digeſt it with Labour; the Savoury Appetite is a greater Mark of the Deity's Favour, than the mighty Treaſure of the luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Man; who like <hi>Tantalus</hi> is ſet in the midſt of Viands, but cannot taſte, he is beſet with Delicacies, but for a Curſe and Reproach, as no way belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him;<hi>—Nulla aconita bibuntur fictilibus, tunc illa time cum pocula ſumis gemmata,</hi> &amp;c. The Cottage fears no Poyſon, the Earthen Pot is fill'd from the Fountain, whilſt their Bowls of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſt Gold carry Death with them; and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30543:41"/>
every Draught is as much Poyſon taken into the Body, in very deed.</p>
            <p>This Crapula has deſtroyed more than Wars or Plague; and though the Miſchiefs that ariſe from Edibles are very many; yet, what ariſe from Drinks are innumerably many more; they are like the Caterpillar and Locuſt, what the one ſpares the other devours, if they are let looſe on the Subject of their Prey. Every one that has ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected himſelf thus miſerably to a bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Luxury, endangers his Health as well as Reputation.</p>
            <p>When this languiſhing Diſtemper, a Conſumption, is conſequential to ſome other Diſeaſe, it is to be duely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd accordingly, that we may ſtrike at the Root of it, on which it grows. <hi>Sic quoniam variant Morbi variabimus artes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Melancholy is often a Cauſe of this Diſtemper: For, a troubled Spirit, who can bear? Sad Thoughts gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in anxious Troops, to afflict the Diſtreſſed; every Perſon being juſt as unhappy as Thoughts ſuggeſt: We find our bleſſed Saviour himſelf complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30543:41"/>
of it: But be what will the Parent of it, Obſtructions are the conſtant Concomitants, or Introductives of it, evident from Reaſon and Experience. It is obſervable, ſome very few Days before Conſumptive Perſons expire, their Coughing and Spitting ceaſes; for, the Blood then being extreamly leſſened by ſeveral Profuſions, hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, can now ſend no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Supply, for a Maintenance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; ſo ſoon after the immortal Soul takes a Departure from its corruptible Manſion.</p>
            <p>A Perſon taking Cold, by lying on the Graſs, ſoon after was ſeiz'd with a violent Coughing and Spitting, which continued for ſome Weeks; he had likewiſe expenſive Sweats in his Sleep, together with Loſs of Appetite, and a viſible Waſting of his Fleſh: He was treated as followeth;</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Sulphuris Antimonii,</hi> gr. v. <hi>Elect. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saſſaphras,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>M. ut fiat Bolus uno vice Sumendus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:30543:42"/>
It gave him Three Vomits, and Two Stools.</p>
            <p>The next Day he had about Eight Ounces of Blood taken from his Arm; and the Day following he began to take Pills Morning and Night, and a reſtorative Drink afterwards.</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Pulv. Piperis albi,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iij. <hi>Vitrioli Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
               <hi>ſs. Balſami Sulphuris aniſati,</hi> ℈j. <hi>Laudani Liquidi, Cydoniat. gut.</hi> xl. <hi>Extract. Gentianae,</hi> q ſ. <hi>ut fiat maſſa pro Pil. Medietat. Magnitud. Doſ.</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> iv. <hi>bis in die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Rad. Sarſaparillae</hi> ℥iij. <hi>Fol. hederae Terreſtris Manip.</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> iij. <hi>coq. in Aquae fontis</hi> 
               <abbr>lb</abbr>vj. <hi>ad Dimid. partis Conſumptionem, doſ.</hi> 
               <abbr>lb</abbr>
               <hi>ſs. omni mane &amp; nocte poſt Pilulas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He continued taking the Pills and Drink for the Space of Three Weeks, during which time he daily grew bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And was at laſt reſtored to his former Health.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:30543:42"/>
A young Man was taken with an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Conſumption, by over-heating his Blood with too much Exerciſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his Body ſoon after to the Air, by ſleeping on a Bench: He was firſt taken with a Fever, afterwards with a violent Coughing and Spitting, which held him for ſome time, and daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed upon him. He requiring my Aſſiſtance, I firſt adviſed him to part with about Ten Ounces of Blood; and at Night to take the following Sudori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Draught:</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Aq. Theriacalis,</hi> ℥iij. <hi>Syr. de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conio,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vj. <hi>M. hora ſomni Sumend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Day he appeared to be ſomewhat better, and his Cough ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what palliated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repetatur hauſtus hac nocte ſumendus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which, being apparently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, I adviſed the following:</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Entis Veneris,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>Extract. Centaur. minor.</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ut fiat maſſa pro Pil.</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> xij. <hi>Cap.</hi> iij. <hi>Omni mane &amp; nocte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:30543:43"/>
℞ <hi>Decoct. Amari ſine Senna,</hi> 
               <abbr>lb</abbr>j. <hi>add. Tartari Vitriolati,</hi> ℈ij. <hi>Doſ.</hi> ℥iv. <hi>bis in die poſt Pilulas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Syrup. de Meconio papar. Errattie ana, ℥jſs. Ol. Amygdal. dulc.</hi> ℥j. <hi>Sacchari penidiati,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>Spr. Sulphuris p. Campan.</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ad Gratum Saporem M. Cochleatim Sumend. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rgente tuſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Method was continued about a Fortnight, to his great Relief; about which time, being taken with a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Looſeneſs, he took the following Clyſter:</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Lactis Vacc.</hi> ℥xiv. <hi>Confect. Fraca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorii,</hi> ℥j. <hi>M. ut fiat enema tepid. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jiciend. hora quarta Pameridiana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Confect. de Hyacinth.</hi> ℈ij. <hi>Terrae Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponicae, croci Martis aſtring. cum, ℈ſs. Theriac. Venet.</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ut fiat Bolus hora ſomni Sumendus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:30543:43"/>
℞ <hi>Spr. Cinnamomi, ℥ſs. Aquae Germ. Quercus,</hi> ℥j<hi>ſs. M. ut fiat hauſtus poſt bolum ſumendus. Repetatur ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Pomeridiana ſequente injiciend. etiamq. Bolus &amp; hauſtus hora ſomni ſumend. Bibat pro potu ordinar. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct. Alb. ſequent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Decoct. Alb.</hi> 
               <abbr>lb</abbr>iij. <hi>Spr. Cinnamomi.</hi> ℥iv. <hi>Syr. è Succo Cydoniorum,</hi> ℥iij. <hi>M. ad uſum dictum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Croci Martis aſtring.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>Balſami Peru. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ſs. Conſervae fructi Cynosbati</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ut fiat maſſa pro pil.</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> xviij. <hi>capiat,</hi> iij<hi>ſ. ter in die horis medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinalibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Cortic. Granat. confract.</hi> ℥j. <hi>flor. Balauſt.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>roſar. rubrar. M.</hi> j. <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namomi acuti contuſ.</hi> ℥j. <hi>coquantur ſimul in Aquae fontis,</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ad</hi> 
               <abbr>lb</abbr>ij. <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laturae ad Syr. de Roſis ſiccis Myrtin. ana,</hi> ℥j<hi>ſs. Spr. Cinnamomi,</hi> ℥iiij. <hi>M. &amp; capiat,</hi> ℥iiij. <hi>ter in die poſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lulas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:30543:44"/>
℞ <hi>Laudani Liquidi Cydoniati</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piat gutt.</hi> viij. <hi>nocte maneq. in hauſt. potus ordinarij.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Method, his Looſneſs was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away in ſome few Days. I then Adviſed the following:</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Salis Martis,</hi> ℈iiij. <hi>Aquae Roſarum dam.</hi> 
               <abbr>lb</abbr>
               <hi>ſs. M. doſ. Cochlear.</hi> j. <hi>omni mane in hauſt. fortis decoctionis Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurij minoris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Laudani Lond.</hi> ℈j. <hi>Balſami Peru.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
               <hi>ſs. Balſami Sulphuris aniſat.</hi> ℈ij. <hi>pulr. cubeb. piperis long. ana,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>extract. Gentianae,</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ut fiat maſſa pro pil.</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> lx. <hi>capiat,</hi> iv <hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>qua<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nocte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I alſo adviſed him to the Country Air. Accordingly he went, and in ſome Time after, return'd to Town in perfect Health. About Eight Years ſince, a Gentleman, living at <hi>Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> from Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly and great Anxiety of Spirit, had brought on himſelf a Conſumption; ſome few Things he had taken in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:30543:44"/>
by the Advice of a Phyſician, but daily grew worſe and worſe. I meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him here, adviſed him to go into <hi>Northamptonſhire</hi> (which if I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake not) was his Native Place, aſſuring him, that Medicines would have much better Effect on him there, then in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> a Place, which when well, he did confeſs, did never agree with him: Having at that Time my ſelf a Dwelling-houſe within Sixteen Miles of him. He deſired me to take Care of him; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly he went into the Country, where I ſoon viſited him: He had a moſt violent Cough, eſpecially in the Night time, and ſpit great Quantities of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent viſcous Phlegm; and when ever he ſlept or ſlumbred, he fell into faint and expenſive Sweats, was for the moſt part Cold and Languid in the extream Parts, as Hands and Feet, a Pain in his Side; was much waſted, and had a Hippocratick Face. I begun with him, as followeth:</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Pulr. Corticis Winteraui cubebar. piperis longi ana,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Salis Martis</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
               <hi>ſs. Balſami Sulphuris aniſat,</hi> ℈ij. <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dani</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:30543:45"/>
               <hi>Liquidi Cydoniat. guit. xl. extr. Gentianae,</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ut fiat Maſſa pro Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lulis Medietatis magnitudinis Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at,</hi> iv. <hi>bis in die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After taking of which he was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what better.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repet. Pil. Specific. ſine ſale Martis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend. ut antea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Limatur. Martis crudi,</hi> ℥iv. <hi>Caryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phillorum, Macis, Zinziberis inciſ. ana,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>j. <hi>Radic. Gentianae inciſ.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iij. <hi>Vini albi,</hi> 
               <abbr>lb</abbr>ij. <hi>Macer. in Balneo Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſpatio Septimanae ſaepe agitando, poſt reſidentiam filtra ad uſum. Doſ. Cochlear.</hi> vj. <hi>Nocte Mane<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſt Pilulas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Pills and Steel-Wine he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued taking for a Month, or Five Weeks, and was recover'd thereby to a great Degree; but preſently return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>London</hi> again, his former Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms encreaſed daily, which ſoon obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to leave the Town, in hopes the Country Air alone might relieve him: As I remember <hi>Norfolk</hi> was the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30543:45"/>
Place, where he ſtaid about a Month; and in his return to <hi>Peterborough,</hi> call'd upon me, at my Houſe in <hi>Wisbich,</hi> in a very weak and bad Condition; he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain implored my Aſſiſtance, I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to do him all the Service I could, by the frequent Adminiſtration of Spices, Chalybeates, Opiates, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaparilla Drinks, Milk-waters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as I ſaw occaſion; but not finding any thing to avail, I declared my Opinion of his Caſe, to be incurable: He after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confulted the ingenious Dr. <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the younger, of <hi>Stamford,</hi> in <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnſhire,</hi> who remarking the extream weak Condition he was in, adviſed him to lay aſide all Medicinal Compoſitions, and betake himſelf to the drinking of the <hi>German</hi> Spaw-water; but growing weaker and weaker, he left off the Uſe of the Spaw-water, and drunk Aſſes Milk to his dying Day, which was ſoon after.</p>
            <p>This Gentleman, on whom this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation is made liv'd under this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper about Eleven Months, which was longer than I ever could obſerve any one to continue, where the Diſeaſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30543:46"/>
terminated in Death. I remember, that he told me, that he had been troubled with a Cough, and frequent Spitting of purulent Matter for ſeveral Years; but without any evident Decay, or Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of his Strength or Fleſh, or Loſs of Appetite, except within the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid time; and, until that appears, I think, we cannot properly pronounce any Perſon to be in a Conſumption.</p>
            <p>A Country Farmer, near <hi>Wisbich,</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> upon the going off of a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, fell into a Cachexia, and ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards grew Tabid: I gave him ſome Pills compoſed of Spices, Balſam of Sulphur, <hi>Aniſated, Ens Veneris, Liquid Laudanum,</hi> and Extract of <hi>Gentian,</hi> drinking a Decoction of <hi>Sarſaparilla,</hi> and <hi>Hedera Terreſtris</hi> after them. Likewiſe, I ordered him a middling ſort of Drink, to be brewed for him, with good ſtore of <hi>Hedera Terreſtris,</hi> to be put into the Copper with the Malt; and in a ſmall time, he regain'd his former Health.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:30543:46"/>
A poor Woman at <hi>Boſton,</hi> in <hi>Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> by taking Cold, was ſeized with a great Pain in her Side, and Difficulty of Breathing, which was ſoon followed with a great Coughing, Spitting and Sweating at Night, in her Sleep; ſhe was much alter'd in her Countenance, and evidently decay'd, and waſted eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day: She took much the ſame Pills as the other, drinking after them an Infuſion of <hi>Semen Sinapi</hi> in Stale-beer, which ſoon took off her Pain in her Side, and much abated the other Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms. Laſtly, I gave her the following Electuary:</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Pulv. Herbae Roriſmarini in Clibano ſiccat, ℥ſs. Mellis Deſpumati,</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ut fiat Electuarium Capiat quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. nucis Moſchatae ter quaterve in die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which, her Coughing, Spitting, and Shortneſs of Breathing, was totally taken away.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:30543:47"/>
A Husbandman near <hi>Dounham,</hi> about Ten Miles diſtant from <hi>Wisbich,</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> from frequent taking Cold, at laſt grew Conſumptive; he cough'd, and ſpit purulent Phlegm very much, eſpecially in the Night time; had faint Sweats in his Sleep; complain'd alſo of a Stoppage at his Stomach, and Pain in his Side; he was much waſted when firſt I ſaw him. I adviſed the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing:</p>
            <p>℞ <hi>Pulv. Piperis albi,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iij. <hi>Balſami Peru.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
               <hi>ſs. Laudani Liquid. gut.</hi> xl. <hi>Extract. Gentianae,</hi> q. ſ. <hi>ut fiat Maſſa pro Pilulis,</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> xxxvj. <hi>Capiat</hi> iv. <hi>quaq mane &amp; nocte ſuperbibendo Cochlear.</hi> vj. <hi>Vint Chalybeati cum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romattie. parat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this he mended apace; for his ordinary Drink, he made uſe of a plain Decoction of <hi>Sarſaparilla,</hi> and <hi>Hedera Terreſtris,</hi> without the Adjunct of any other Ingredient; and, in about Six Weeks time, he was reſtored to his former Health. For a Reſtorative Dyet, I adviſed him to a ſtrong Broath, made
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30543:47"/>
of the Lean of a Leg of Pork, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned very high with a great Quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Pepper, and moderately with Salt.</p>
            <p>A near Neighbour of mine, now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, about Ten Years ago, was far gone in a Conſumption, he was cured by a ſtrong Decoction of Spices, <hi>Cortex Peru</hi> intermixt with <hi>Chalybeates,</hi> and <hi>Opiates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could inſert more of the like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and cured much after the ſame Manner; but, for Brevity ſake, I ſhall omit them.</p>
            <p>We ſhall next inſert a <hi>Materia Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica,</hi> from which an experienc'd Perſon may form ſuch Compoſitions, as are ſuitable to the Cauſe, Symptoms, and Conſtitution of his Patient, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Radix Jalapae, vel Mechocannae nigrae, Rhabarbari, allii, Sarſaparillae, Chinae, Enulae Campanae, ſymphyti, eringii, Capparum, ari, Raphani ſylveſtris, Gentianae, Zinziberis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:30543:48"/>
               <hi>Folia Satureiae, Cardui benedicti, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurii Minoris, abſinthii vulgaris, Thymi, Majoranae, Salviae, anthos, Hyſſopi, Tuſſila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis, Capillorum Veneris, Hederae Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtris Pulegii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cortex Peru; Tamariſci. Balſam. Peru, Crocus Britanicus, limaces, Icthiocolla, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perae, Ambragiſea, Terra Japonica, Aloes, Succotrina, capita papaverum alborum. Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per nigrum, Macis, Mars crud. Flores Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum Rubrarum. Balauſtiarum, Semina Aniſi, cannabis, recentis, ſinapi. Aquae Minerales, vinum Scillitticum, Oxymel Scillitticum, Pil. de Cynogloſſa, Laudanum Londinenſis, Elixar Proprietatis, Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Sulphuris Aniſatum Tinctura Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſami Sulphuris Aniſati, Spiritus Sanguinis Humani, Sulphur Antimonii auratum, Sal Martis ens Veneris, Sal Nitri, Tartarum Vitriolatum,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But, before we take our leave of this Treatiſe, we cannot omit taking Notice of a general Error among many People, as to the Duration of a Pthiſis, or Conſumption, which they alledge often to be of many Years continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and are not wanting, in relating
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30543:48"/>
Inſtances and Examples of that Kind: But, as we ſaid before, the uſual Stage of it is (for the moſt part) ſhort of a Year, but never beyond, as ever we could obſerve on many Inſtances, but what terminated within that time, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a State of Health or Mortality; for, though ſome People may cough and ſpit a Quantity of Flegm for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Years together, yet, while their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite remains reaſonably good, their Digeſtion laudable, and are free from any of the other Profuſions and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of Nature, incident to this Caſe, without any ſenſible Decay of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as to Bulk or Strength, they can in no wiſe be properly ſaid to be in a Conſumption, although inclinable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and on the leaſt Occaſion may ſlide into a Confirmation of it.</p>
            <p>In a Word, Conſumptions are to be cured (where the Party is not too far gone) by Meaſures far different to thoſe of the Ancients, by a Method abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly free from all nauſeous Sweets, which clogs and vitiates the Stomach, and deſtroys the Appetite; and more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Coolers, which create Stoppages
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:30543:49"/>
in the Blood, and cauſe it to ſuffer in the higheſt Degree of Degeneracy and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Brisk, active, attenuating Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, being the only Adequates, to cope with this Diſtemper; and ſhall often (contrary to all reaſonable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation) effect a Cure.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:30543:49"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>PUrging Pills which Cure the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Diſtemper,</hi> and <hi>Scurvey,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of Confinement, or Diſturbance to the Body, and prevents the Infection from getting up into the Head; purges alſo the Head, Limbs, and Urinary Paſſages. At Three Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings the Box, with Directions.</p>
            <p>Dyet-Drink at Eighteen-pence the Quart; or Papers of Ingredients to make it, at Eighteen-pence each Paper, which will keep without loſing their Vertue a long Time; the Drink is pleaſant and grateful to the Palate, cleanſes and ſweetens the whole Maſs of Blood, from the Scurvey and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Infection: Alſo, the immoderate Uſe of <hi>Mercury,</hi> with Directions; ſuch as cannot be Confined, may be Cured without Fluxing, Danger, or Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thoſe who deſire it, may have it performed after the ſafeſt and moſt effectual Manner, by <hi>T. Nedham,</hi> at his Houſe, the <hi>Surgeons</hi> Sign, in <hi>Windſor-Court,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30543:50"/>
in <hi>Drury-Lane,</hi> near the <hi>Dog-Tavern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> He hath a particular Method, which ſpeedily and effectually Cures moſt inveterate Ulcers, in any Part of the Body, ſtubborn and rebellious Scabs, running Sores, or any Breaking out: Alſo, the <hi>King</hi>'s<hi>-Evil,</hi> all <hi>Fiſtula</hi>'s, that are curable, having ſufficiently experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd the ſame Abroad, in His Majeſty's Service, where no one Perſon was left by me uncured; and all People may generally expect a Certainty thereof, where there ſhall be a Poſſibility of it, by <hi>T. N.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30543:50"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
